SAQIB SARWAR

2/265A Sector L, Aashiyana, Lucknow. UP. India. 226012

■ 9532053622 | Saqib@cse.iitk.ac.in | Asaqib-sarwar.github.io | Github.com/saqib-sarwar | SSK | Inclinkedin.com/in/saqib-sarwar-3b26a5222 |

k saqibsarwarkhan | 🕿 Saqib Sarwar

"And your Lord never forgets."

Personal Profile

I am a doctoral student with Prof. Piyush Rai in Dept. Of Computer Science & Engineering at IIT Kanpur. I work in the area of general machine learning, deep learning, computer vision and natural language processing. I am a recipient of the prestigious Visvesvaraya PhD Fellowship. Prior to joining IIT Kanpur, I worked as a Project Associate II on a DST sponsored project funded by C3iHub. I have completed my Master's and Bachelor's from Dept. Of Computer Engineering at AMU.

Education

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

Kanpur, India

PhD in Computer Science and Engineering

Jan 2023 - Current

• Recipient of Visvesvaraya PhD Fellowship

Aligarh Muslim University

Aligarh, India

Aug 2019 - Dec 2021

M.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering

• Graduated with Distinction

• M.Tech Thesis - "Risk factors classification for Appropriate Screening of Cervical Cancer."

Aligarh Muslim University

Aligarh, India

BTech in Computer Engineering

Aug 2013 - June 2017

· Graduated First Division

Lucknow Public School

Lucknow, India

High School

Apr 2009 - Apr 2010

- · Passed with Distinction
- Specialised in Physics, Chemistry, and Maths with Computer Science

Work Experience

Institute of Engineering and Technology

Lucknow, India

Project Associate II

Apr 2022 - Dec 2022

- Designed a visualisation module to perform comparative univariate & bivariate analysis and multivariate correlation between real and synthetic
 data.
- Implemented state-of-the-art Copula and GAN models for synthetic data generation.
- Technical Skills: Python with PyTorch, NumPy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Ubuntu Linux, Git, VS Code.
- Soft Skills: Time Management, Communication, Presentation skills.

String Social Networks Pvt. Ltd.

Delhi, India

Android Developer

July 2017 - June 2019

- Developed News based social media app NewsGallery on MVVM pattern.
- Technical Skills: Java, Kotlin, Retrofit, LiveData, ViewModel, Push Notifications, Glide, Coroutines, Git, Android Studio.
- Soft Skills: Teamwork, Time Management, Communication.

Academic Experience

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

Kanpur, India

Jan 2023 - Apr 2023

Teaching Assisstant

Teaching Assisstant

• CS253: Software Development and Operations (2024, 2023)

- Successfully organized an online Machine Learning Competition on Kaggle

• CS771: Intro to Machine Learning (2024, 2023)

Aligarh Muslim University

Aligarh, India

Aug 2019 - Dec 2019

• Network and Embedded Systems Lab

DECEMBER 19, 2024

University Projects

Hindi to English Machine Translation

Kanpur, India

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

Apr 2023

- · Developed a Machine translation model based on Transformers to translate English Sentences to Hindi
- Achieved a decent BLEU score of 0.15 for hindi-english translation

Sentiment Analysis Kanpur, India

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

Apr 2023

• Designed and implemented various sentiment analysis models using FastText, RNNs and LSTM.

Plant Leaves Disease Detection and Classification

Kanpur, India

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

Mar 2023 - Apr 2023

- Used State of the art Image classification models Resnet, EfficientNet, MobileNetV3 for plant disease detection.
- · Created a custom dataset of healthy and unhealthy plant leaves in real life conditions with 8 species and 16 classes.
- Used Visual AI methods Grad-CAM, Grad-CAM++, ScoreCam to explain model performance

Skills

ProgrammingPython (Pandas, PyTorch, NumPy, Scikit-learn. etc.), Java, C/C++, Kotlin, SQL.MiscellaneousLinux, McX(Overleaf), Android Studio, VS Code, Microsoft Office, Firebase, Git.Soft SkillsTime Management, Teamwork, Problem-solving, Logical Thinking, Presentation.

Achievements

2023	Recipient , Visvesvaraya PhD Fellowship	India
2022	(196/300) JRF, UGC NET	India
2020	PGT, HTET CS	India
2018	Rank 28, JEST (IMSc)	India
2017	Rank 32, JEST (IMSc)	India
2017	98 percentile, GATE CSE	India

Publications

Simple and Scalable Federated Learning with Uncertainty via Improved Variational Online Newton

Shivam Pal, Aishwarya Gupta, Saqib Sarwar, Piyush Rai

OPT 2024: Optimization for Machine Learning (2024). 2024

Predicting Influent and Effluent Quality Parameters for a UASB-Based Wastewater Treatment Plant in Asia Covering Data Variations during COVID-19: A Machine Learning Approach

Parul Yadav, Manik Chandra, Nishat Fatima, Saqib Sarwar, Aditya Chaudhary, Kumar Saurabh, Brijesh Singh Yadav *Water* 15.4 (2023) p. 710.2023

Qualitative and Quantitative Evaluation of Multivariate Time-Series Synthetic Data Generated Using MTS-TGAN: A Novel Approach Parul Yadav, Manish Gaur, Nishat Fatima, Saqib Sarwar

Applied Sciences 13.7 (2023) p. 4136. 2023

Certifications

Nov 2022 **Deep Learning: Image Recognition, LinkedIn Learning**

Nov 2022 SQL for Data Analysis, LinkedIn Learning

Oct 2022 Data Science with Python, Skillup by Simplilearn

May 2022 **Computer Vision**, Kaggle

May 2022 Intro to Deep Learning, Kaggle

Interests

Photography Though I do not have a professional camera, some of my decent snaps can be found on Instagram here.
 Altruism I like contributing in different venues of life. One such example is being a Google Local Guide (Level 9).
 Badminton My interest in this sport began during my first year in bachelors. Since then, I have learned a lot.

DECEMBER 19, 2024 2